Congresswoman Lynn Schenk papers LSC.2209
UCLA Library Special Collections
Congresswoman Lynn Schenk papers
Bulk, 1992-2004
1959-2005
LSC.2209
UCLA Library Special Collections
21.0 linear feet (21 record cartons)
Lynn Schenk is a lawyer and politician who served one term in the U.S. House of Representatives as a congresswoman from San Diego. She also served as Chief of Staff to Gray Davis during his entire tenure as Governor of California. The collection consists mostly of material from these offices, including subject files, correspondence, and administrative records. There is also material relating to several political campaigns, including Schenk's own, the 2003 gubernatorial recall, and the 2004 presidential race.
Schenk, Lynn, 1945-
Conditions on Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Open for research. Advance notice required for access. Contact the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk for paging information.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 8034329
Biography/History
Lynn Schenk was born on January 5, 1945 in the Bronx, New York. The daughter of immigrants from Eastern Europe, she and her family moved westward, finally settling in Los Angeles. Schenk received a BA from UCLA, and then earned her law degree at the University of San Diego. Politically and socially active, in 1972 she co-founded the Lawyers Club of San Diego as an organization to support female lawyers and to advocate for women's rights in general. In 1975, she was appointed a White House Fellow and worked for three years in the Office of the Vice President. In 1992, she ran for the U.S. Congress in a newly created district that encompassed most of San Diego. When she won, she became the first woman ever elected to the House of Representatives from the city, and the first Democrat in forty years. Though she lost her reelection bid in 1994, she remained active in Democratic and California politics. In 1998, governor-elect Gray Davis asked her to serve as his Chief of Staff, and she remained in that role until Davis was recalled in 2003.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of material relating to the political career of Lynn Schenk, especially her term as a member of the U.S. House of Representatives and her position as Chief of Staff to California governor Gray Davis. There are subject files with information about issues important to voters, as well as administrative files regarding the operations of various offices. There is correspondence from constituents, lobbyists, and other political figures. The collection also contains a great deal of material on campaigns, including the successful effort to recall Davis from office, and the 2004 presidential race, during which Schenk was an important fundraiser for John Kerry. Also represented are Schenk's unsuccessful bids for the San Diego County Board of Supervisors and California attorney general. There is also a small amount of personal material.
Organization and Arrangement
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1. Chief of Staff files
Series 2. U.S. Congress files
Series 3. White House Fellows files
Series 4. California Attorney General files
Series 5. San Diego County Board of Supervisors files
Series 6. Kerry/Edwards campaign files
Series 7. Personal files
Separated Material
Political Cartoons and Caricatures from the Collection of Michael Alexander Kahn (New York: The Grolier Club, 2007).
Schenk, Lynn, 1945- -- Archives; California--Politics and government.; Lawyers--California--San Diego--Archives.; United States. Congress. House
- Series 1. Chief of Staff files, 1998-2003
  Scope and Content
  This series contains material from Schenk's tenure as Chief of Staff to California governor Gray Davis.
  - Subject files, 1999-2003
    Organization and Arrangement
    Files are maintained in their original order.
    This subseries includes material relating to a variety of topics, both political and administrative.
    - Zedillo, Ernesto, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - IDEC Pharmaceuticals, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Apartment, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Tribal-State Gaming Compact, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Photographs - portraits of Schenk, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Remcho, Joe, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Strategy retreat, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Governors retreat, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Saban, Haim and Cheryl, 1999-2002 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Appointments and staffing, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Governor's organizational chart, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Bear pin, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Revenues, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Staffing issues, 1999-2003 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Transportation, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Phil Trounstine speech [to the Democratic Leadership Council], 2001 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - First Lady's pin, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Senior staff meetings, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Democratic National Convention, 2000 (Box 1, Folders 19-21)
    - Proposition 40, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - 2002 budget, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Macarro, Mark [Pechanga Band of Luiseno Indians], 2000 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Malcolm, David, 2001-2003 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - San Diego traffic congestion relief plan, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Revai, Gabriela - recommendation, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Jefferson-Jackson Dinner speech, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - High-speed ferry, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Fox, Vicente - visit, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Energy crisis, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Democratic Governors Association - Seattle, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - New York in July, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - I-5/I-805 widening project, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Legal Aid Society of San Diego, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Staff retreat, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Reapportionment, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - San Diego Union-Tribune "Stake" article/editorial, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Democratic governors and Chiefs of Staff, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Chief of Staff lunch thank-yous, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - National Governors Conference, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - San Diego Dialogue's McGill Circle breakfast, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Lantos, Congressman Tom, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Prison wardens, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Inauguration, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Abortion, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Biocom San Diego, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Bioscience, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - SBC Pacific Bell - new regulatory framework, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - National Governors Association, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Issues: Agriculture / African-American / Asian-American / Business, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Issues: Civil Rights / Consumers / Education / Environment, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Issues: Gay/Lesbian / Good Government / Health Care / Housing, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Issues: Human Services / Innovative Government / Labor / Latino/a, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Issues: Local Government / Major Cities and Regions / Native Americans / Public Safety, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Issues: Rural Areas / Seniors / Terrorism, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Issues: Transportation / Veterans / Women, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - San Diego State Office Building, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - California Tribal Census Project, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Meeting the Energy Challenge, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Governor Gray Davis [booklet touting his accomplishments], 2001 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - California Statewide Survey for Governor Gray Davis [polling data], 1999 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Proposed reductions, 2002-2003, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Border security, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Environmental Impact Statement for the Completion of the 14-Mile Border Infrastructure System, San Diego, California, 2002 (Box 2, Folders 15-16)
    - Personnel, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Kerry, John, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Lantos, Tom, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Appointments by Governor Gray Davis, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Resumes and bios [of Schenk and her husband, Hugh Friedman], 1995-1998 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Lists, 1999-2001 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Governor's business meetings, 1999-2002 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Re-election, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Commission on Industrial Innovation, 1982-1999 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Keene, Barry, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Gray Davis photographs, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents note
      Contains proof sheets from events opposing Davis's recall; participants include Warren Beatty, Annette Bening, Jack Nicholson, Bruce Wilis, Jesse Jackson.
    - San Diego issues, 1999-2001 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Talking points, 1999-2003 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Science and Technology Council, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Cabinet conflicts notification, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Third party bad faith, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - UCLA magazine interview, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - San Diego City schools, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - San Diego budget requests, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Gilmore Commission Report on Terrorism, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Center for Medicinal Cannabis Research, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - California Council on Science and Technology, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Morongo Band of Mission Indians, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Price Movements in California Exchange Markets, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Accomplishments, 1999-2003 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Weekly meetings, 2003 (Box 3, Folders 16-21)
    - Staffing, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Lehane, Chris and Mark Fabiani, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Security accomplishments, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - San Diego Children's Hospital, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - High-speed rail, 1999 (Box 3, Folders 26-27)
    - Hamilton High reunion, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Holmes, Dr. Edward W., 2002 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Inauguration, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - White House Fellows Program, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Judicial appointments, 1999-2003 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Recall, 2003 (Box 3, Folders 33-34, Box 4, Folders 1-3)
    - Letters of recommendation, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Transition, 2003 (Box 4, Folders 5-6)
    - Transition 2003: California State Agencies, Departments, Boards and Commissions (Box 4, Folders 7-8)
    - Last Days, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      Includes copy of a letter from Gray Davis to Arnold Schwarzenegger.
    - Notes written on posters, undated (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, 1998-2003
    Incoming correspondence (which is usually accompanied by a response) is organized by month from December, 1998 to November, 2001, although January-March, 1999 is missing. After that, the correspondence is only minimally present, and unsorted. Outgoing correspondence (which consists only of copies of Schenk's replies, which are often handwritten) is well-sorted for 2000 and roughly chronological for 2001.
    - Incoming correspondence, 1998-1999 (Boxes 4-5)
    - Incoming correspondence, 2000 (Boxes 5-6)
    - Incoming correspondence, 2001 (Boxes 6-7)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1999-2003 (Box 7)
    - Outgoing correspondence, 1999-2001 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous invitations, 1999-2003 (Box 8)
  - Office files, 1999-2003
    - Phone call sheets, 1999 (Box 8)
    - Phone call sheets, 1999-2001 (Box 9)
    - Phone call sheets, 2002-2003 (Box 10)
    - To-Do lists, 2001-2003 (Box 10)
    - Calendars and schedules, 1999-2001 (Box 10)
    - Business cards, undated (Box 11)
    - Rolodex cards, undated (Box 11)
    - Ephemera, 2000-2003 (Box 11)
    - Pins, undated (Box 11)
      Two pins in the shape of California designed for Gray and Sharon Davis by the Franklin Mint.
    - Stationery, undated (Box 11)
  - Videotapes, 2001-2003
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    SUBSERIES CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials in this subseries will require assessment and possible digitization for safe access. To review these audiovisual materials, you must notify the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk in advance of your visit.
    - VHS tapes, 2001-2003 (Box 12)
      Twelve cassettes.
      FILE CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials in this file will require assessment and possible digitization for safe access. To review these audiovisual materials, you must notify the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk in advance of your visit.
- Series 2. U.S. Congress files, 1992-1994
  This series contains material regarding Schenk's term in the U.S. House of Representatives, and the election campaigns associated with it.
  - Campaign files, 1992-1994
    - Office lease, 1992 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Polling data, 1994 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Campaign, 1992 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Campaign budget, 1992 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Campaign contributors, 1992 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Campaign statement [financial], 1992 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Georgiou, Byron, 1992-1993 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Wise, Jim [financial], 1993 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - 49th congressional district study [polling data], 1994 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Receipts and disbursements, 1994 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Fundraising campaign, 1994 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Campaign budget, 1994 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Contribution summary, 1994 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Faxed stuff, 1994 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Strategy and poll, 1994 (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Latest budget, 1994 (Box 13, Folder 16)
    - Lynn Schenk for Congress, 1994 (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - Bilbray, Brian, 1994 (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - Bilbray, Brian - campaign research, 1994 (Box 15, Folders 19-21)
    - Clippings, 1992 (Box 13, Folders 22-23)
    - Donor records and financial documents, 1994 (Box 18)
  - Legislative files, 1992-1994
    Files are maintained in original order.
    - Congress orientation, 1992 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - New member directories, 1992 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Highlights of House ethics rules, undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Clinton [Bill and Hillary] photos, circa 1992 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Congratulatory letters sent, 1993 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Congratulatory letters received, 1992 (Box 14, Folders 6-8)
    - Abortion, 1994 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Advisory committees, 1993 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Airline list, undated (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Airport, 1993 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Base closure, 1993 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Base closures - successful, 1993 (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Biomedical, 1993-1994 (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Biomedical advisory, 1993-1994 (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - Biotech, 1993 (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - Border Environment Cooperation Commission, 1993 (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Breakthrough drug, 1994 (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - Brennan, Ed, 1993 (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - Business roundtable, 1993-1994 (Box 14, Folder 21)
    - Cable Association, 1994 (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - Cargo preference, 1994 (Box 14, Folder 23)
    - Chamber of Commerce lunch, 1994 (Box 14, Folder 24)
    - Clean air, 1994 (Box 14, Folder 25)
    - Clean water, 1993 (Box 14, Folder 26)
    - Clean Water Act, 1993 (Box 14, Folder 27)
    - Clinton, Hillary - visit, 1994 (Box 14, Folder 28)
    - Dept. of Commerce Grant - San Diego World Trade Center, 1994 (Box 14, Folder 29)
    - Congressional Ethics Reform Act, 1994 (Box 14, Folder 30)
    - Constituent complaints, 1994 (Box 14, Folder 31)
    - Coronado, 1994 (Box 14, Folder 32)
    - Cruise ship, 1994 (Box 14, Folder 33)
    - Defense conversion, 1994 (Box 14, Folder 34)
    - Dellums, Ron - visit, 1993 (Box 14, Folder 35)
    - Democratic clubs, undated (Box 14, Folder 36)
    - Democratic Leadership Council, 1993 (Box 14, Folder 37)
    - Epstein, Tom, 1994 (Box 14, Folder 38)
    - Environmental Protection Agency, 1994 (Box 14, Folder 39)
    - Environmental Protection Agency office, 1994 (Box 14, Folder 40)
    - Finance, 1994 (Box 14, Folder 41)
    - Gay and lesbian advisory, 1993 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Gore, Al - visit, 1993 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Gore, Al - visit, 1994 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Gun control, 1993-1994 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Guns in school, 1994 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Health care reform, 1993 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Health care symposium, 1993 (Box 15, Folders 7-8)
    - Hedgecock, Roger, 1993 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Hodgdon, Sharon, 1994 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - International Boundary and Water Commission, 1994 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Imperial Beach Chamber of Commerce, undated (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Immigration, 1993-1994 (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Inauguration tickets, 1993 (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - Japanese contacts, 1993 (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - Kaiser Permanente, 1994 (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - Kudos, 1993-1994 (Box 15, Folder 17)
    - Kudos - business, 1993-1994 (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - Kudos - constituents, 1994 (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - Kudos - government officials, 1993 (Box 15, Folder 20)
    - Kudos - personal, 1993 (Box 15, Folder 21)
    - Kudos - personal, 1994 (Box 15, Folder 22)
    - Labor, 1994 (Box 15, Folder 23)
    - Letters from members, 1992 (Box 15, Folder 24)
    - Letters - miscellaneous, 1993-1994 (Box 15, Folders 25-26)
    - Mail counts, 1993 (Box 15, Folder 27)
    - Memories, 1994 (Box 15, Folder 28)
    - USS Monsoon, 1993 (Box 15, Folder 29)
    - Shipbuilding, 1993-1994 (Box 15, Folder 30)
    - Administrative briefings, 1994 (Box 15, Folder 31)
    - Articles, 1994 (Box 15, Folder 32)
    - Newsletters, 1994 (Box 15, Folder 33)
    - Lexis-Nexis search results, 1994 (Box 15, Folder 34)
    - Scorecards and ratings, 1994 (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - Votes, 1994 (Box 16, Folders 1-2)
    - Legislative staus reports, 1994 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Budget 1993, 1986-1992 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Budget info, 1993-1994 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1993-1994 (Box 16, Folders 5-14)
    - VIP mail, 1994 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Letters after November '94 election, 1994 (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - The Economy under President Clinton: the First Twenty Months, 1994 (Box 16, Folder 17)
    - Manual on the Federal Budget Process, 1991-1993 (Box 16, Folder 18)
    - Guest book, 1993-1994 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Schedules, 1993 (Box 17, Folders 2-16)
- Series 3. White House Fellows files, 1975-1977
  This series contains material related to Schenk's time as a White House Fellow, working in the office of the Vice President of the United States under both Nelson Rockefeller and Walter Mondale. The material primarily concerns staff and office procedures.
  - Rockefeller, Nelson, 1975-1976 (Box 17, Folder 17)
  - Mondale, Walter, 1977 (Box 17, Folder 18)
- Series 4. California Attorney General files, 1998
  This series contains material relating to Schenk's campaign for California Attorney General.
  - Environment, 1998 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Congressional consumer record, 1998 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Questionnaires, 1998 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Notes on speeches, 1998 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Crime, cops, etc, 1998 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Labor, 1998 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Gay record, 1998 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Tobacco record, 1998 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Thank yous, 1997 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Alliance speech, 1998 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper articles, 1998 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Press, 1998 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Endorsement letters, 1998 (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Bios, 1998 (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - Mailers, 1998 (Box 19, Folder 15)
  - Fundraising, 1998 (Box 19, Folder 16)
  - Polling data, 1998 (Box 19, Folder 17)
  - Consultants, 1998 (Box 19, Folder 18)
  - Schedule, 1998 (Box 19, Folder 19)
  - News releases, 1998 (Box 19, Folder 20)
- Series 5. San Diego County Board of Supervisors files, 1984
  This series consists of material relating to Schenk's campaign to join the San Diego County Board of Supervisors.
  - Donations, 1984 (Box 19, Folders 21-29)
  - Correspondence, 1984 (Box 20, Folders 1-5)
- Series 6. Kerry/Edwards campaign files, 2004
  This series contains material on the 2004 U.S. presidential election, during which Schenk was a very active trustee for the John Kerry campaign. It consists mostly of documents related to a variety of fundraising events across the country.
  - Correspondence and fundraisers, 2004 (Box 20)
- Series 7. Personal files, 1959-2005
  This series contains material not connected to a specific job or campaign.
  - Correspondence, 2004-2005 (Box 21, Folders 1-2)
  - To-do lists, 2004-2005 (Box 21, Folders 3-6)
  - Calls to make, 2004-2005 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Kyoto laureate symposium, 2005 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Travel, 2005 (Box 21, Folders 9-10)
  - Gray Davis dinner, 2005 (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Presidential inauguration, 2005 (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - Democratic Senatorial Campaign Committee, 2005 (Box 21, Folder 13)
  - Proposition 63, 2005 (Box 21, Folder 14)
  - Phil Angelides luncheon, 2005 (Box 21, Folder 15)
  - Lawyers Club, 1996-2007 (Box 21, Folder 16)
  - Jewish issues, 1959-1990 (Box 21, Folder 17)
  - Periodicals and clippings, 1993-2003 (Box 21, Folder 18)
  - Luncheons, 2005-2006 (Box 21, Folder 19)
  - Jury duty, 2001 (Box 21, Folder 20)